<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Getting_Started">
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  <para>
    This chapter provides a brief introduction to &PRODUCT; and its usage, and covers how to create, configure, manage, and build a full-featured blog.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      On GNU/Linux, UNIX, and similar operating systems, you can use <command>blaze-<replaceable>command</replaceable></command> and more convenient <command>blaze <replaceable>command</replaceable></command> interchangeably. For a list of available commands, type the following at a shell prompt:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze help</command></screen>
  </note>
  <section id="sect-Getting_Started-Creating">
    <title>Creating a New Blog</title>
    <para>
      To create a new blog, move into the directory in which you want to keep its working copy, and type:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-init</command>
Created a BlazeBlogger repository in .blaze.</screen>
    <para>
      This will create a hidden directory, <filename class="directory">.blaze/</filename>, in which the blog data will be stored. The actual content of this directory is not important, and it is recommended that you never touch the files in it directly. To recover its content should it ever be damaged, use the same command again:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-init</command>
Recovered a BlazeBlogger repository in .blaze.</screen>
    <para>
      You can also revert the existing configuration, theme, and language files to their initial state by supplying the <option>--force</option> (or <option>-f</option> for short) command line option:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-init -f</command>
Recovered a BlazeBlogger repository in .blaze.</screen>
    <para>
      For a complete list of available command line options, refer to <xref linkend="sect-Core_Utilities-init" />.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Getting_Started-Stats">
    <title>Displaying Blog Statistics</title>
    <para>
      To display detailed information about the blog statistics, including the total number of blog posts and pages, the date of the very first blog post, and the date of the latest published post, use the <command>blaze-list</command> with the <option>--stats</option> (or shorter <option>-S</option>) option:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-list -S</command>
Number of pages: 5
Number of posts: 11
Last post date:  2010-07-25
First post date: 2009-02-10</screen>
    <para>
      You can also display the short version of the above output by supplying the <option>--short</option> (or <option>-s</option>) command line option as well:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-list -Ss</command>
There is a total number of 11 blog posts and 5 pages in the repository.</screen>
  </section>
  <section id="sect-Getting_Started-Log">
    <title>Displaying a Log</title>
    <para>
      For the possibility of a future review, &PRODUCT; keeps track of all significant changes to the blog, including its initialization and recovery, addition of new content, changes to existing blog posts and pages, and their removal.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        Since version 0.9.0, &PRODUCT; allows you to enable a colored output for some of its utilites. To enable this feature for <command>blaze-log</command>, use the following command:
      </para>
      <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-config color.log true</command></screen>
    </note>
    <para>
      To display the complete history of the blog, type the following at a shell prompt:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-log</command>
Date: Sun Jul 25 16:48:22 2010

    Edited the page with ID 5.

Date: Tue Jul  6 18:54:59 2010

    Edited the page with ID 5.

<emphasis>etc.</emphasis></screen>
    <para>
      By default, log entries are sorted from the newest to oldest, so that the latest change is listed at the top. If you prefer the reverse order, use the <option>--reverse</option> (or <option>-r</option>) command line option:
    </para>
        <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-log -r</command>
Date: Tue Feb 10 00:40:16 2009

    Created/recovered a BlazeBlogger repository.

Date: Tue Feb 10 01:06:44 2009

    Added the page with ID 1.

<emphasis>etc.</emphasis></screen>
    <para>
      Finally, to display only a limited number of log entries, use the <option>--number</option> (or <option>-n</option> for short) command line option. For example, to display the latest change to the blog, type:
    </para>
    <screen>~]$ <command>blaze-log -n 1</command>
Date: Sun Jul 25 16:48:22 2010

    Edited the page with ID 5.

</screen>
    <para>
      For a complete list of available command line options, refer to <xref linkend="sect-Core_Utilities-log" />.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
